In this lesson we're going to be exploring a super powerful feature of TypeScript,
which is functions as types and callbacks. By the end of this lesson you're going to
understand how to type functions, how to pass functions into other functions,
and how TypeScript helps prevent bugs before your code even runs.
So what does exactly does functions as types mean? So in JavaScript functions are first-class
citizens, that means you can store them in variables, pass them to other functions,
and return them from other functions. TypeScript extends this idea by letting us describe
a function shape using types. So let's start with a very simple example. Let's do function,
add, a is a number, and b is a number.
I'm simply going to return a plus b.
Now we've typed the parameters and the return value is inferred.
But what if we want to store this function as a variable?
We can simply do this, we can do let my function,
and we give it the parameters say x and there's a number, and y is a number,
and this is going to return with an arrow, syntax, a number.
So this align means that my function is a function that takes two numbers as a parameter
and returns a number. Now let's assign a function to it, so we can say my function equals add.
Now because function add also has two parameters of both of which are numbers,
and it returns a number, which is inferred, it could be assigned to this function because it matches
the same type as these guys here. Type2ups are going to allow this because the types match
the function signature. And if we try to assign a function with the wrong types,
TypeScript is going to immediately warn us. Now function signatures can get quite long,
so TypeScript allows us to simplify them using type aliases.
So let's just take this a bit further, and we're going to rename our function here,
by a function number is going to change it, so we're going to change this from my function
to math operation, and we need to change this to a type alias by just defining it as a type.
So we have a math operation, and we still need to make this an equals sign, equals number,
and a number, so this is no a type alias. So what we can do now is we can define some
constants and say, say, subtract operation, and the operation subtract is a type math operation,
which has two parameters, a and b, which is going to map up with the x and y on the math operation
here, then we define with the actual implementation of that operation, so you can say a minus b.
And we can do the same thing we could have more to apply.
It's also a math operation receives in two properties, a and b,
and then we define the implementation of that, so a times b, oops, b.
So this makes our cloud so much cleaner and much more reasonable, especially when we have
multiple functions that share the same structure that we have up here.
Now that we know that functions can be treated like data, we can then pass them
into other functions, and this is called a callback. So callback is just a function that lets you
pass to another function so that the receiving function can call it later.
And there are some examples of this, for example, you may be aware of the operation.map on an array,
dot map, so this uses a callback, which we defined.
Also have things like event listeners, they also use callbacks, as well as things like a synchronous
code can often use callback. So let's create a function that accepts another function,
so we can do function, it's called greet, and this is going to have a name and a formatter.
So this format that's going to be our callback function is going to also have a name,
and this is going to return string.
So that's the end of our greet, greet function, and the greet function itself is also going to
infer that it's going to return a string. Now we can do return, say hello, plus we can call our
all matter function, and pass the name parameter to it.
So formatter is a callback, and it must be a function that takes a string and returns a string
as the beast can be seen here. So now we can actually create that formatter,
so we could have function, say to upper case,
this will receive a name, and all we do is return name to upper case.
So now it means we can recall our greet function and do greet,
and supply a name, let's say Alice, and we supply our function to upper case,
which is going to match the signature on this defined here, which takes a name and returns a string,
and that becomes two upper case. Let's not execute that, and we get hello Alice in upper case.
Now if we were to try and pass that callback with a wrong structure,
TypeScript's going to prevent the errors early, so let's try and do something and break it,
and it's going to come into here, and we're going to say going to send a value n, which is going
to be a value, one, two, three, and it's going to complain because it's not a signable to a string.
So just like before, callback types can also be extracted into the own type alias.
So let's just quickly undo this code, and let's take an example, so we have this formatter to
find up here, and instead of defining what we have our actual formatter here, let's cut up to
here and do type name formatter, or matter. This is going to take name string, and it's going to
return a string. And now we have to find the type alias, we can remove what we have here,
and change it just to name formatter. As this, as you can probably see, makes our code so much
easier to read and maintain, especially when we have much larger code bases. Let's next have a look
at a typical real world callback example, and this is going to be used and things like simulating
API requests. So you have a function, say fetch data, this will receive a callback,
and the callback is going to receive data as string, and the callbacks not going to return
anything, so we can just say returns void. We're going to call the straightforward set timeout,
so it's simulating API call here, and then we're going to receive our data,
and we're going to call our callback, and say here is the data, and then we just say after one
thousand at milliseconds. So the callback itself type says this function receives a string,
and then returns nothing, so this is the definition of the callback here.
Now let's actually recall this, so we can do fetch data, and we can say we're going to
supply data, and the data is then going to, while we receive the data, we're going to then
have a callback, which is going to log to the console, our data received, and then supply the
data itself, and of course that should be fetch data with a capital letter, there we go.
So this here code is only going to be called once the data arrives via the callback,
and this is exactly how older no JES API works, and it's still extremely common in front end frameworks.
Okay, so time for a quick recap, so in TypeScript, functions can be treated as values,
and we can also describe a function shape using function types, and CoreX are just functions
passed into other functions. TypeScript also ensures the callbacks are matched to the expected
signature, and we define an example of a callback signature here, and type aliases, as you've seen,
makes our functions types much easier to use.